Nathaniel Sisson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Nathaniel Sisson Papers 1838-1932 (bulk 1862-1920)
MSS85304
Sisson, Nathaniel, 1845-1932
1,100 items
10 containers plus 4 oversize
6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Union soldier and businessman. Correspondence, financial records, medals, printed matter, and writings pertaining to Sisson’s Civil War service, political activities, and business enterprises in Maryville, Missouri.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Sisson family.; Sisson, Nathaniel, 1845-1932.
Organizations
Freemasons.
Subjects
Agriculture.; Bridges--Design and construction.; Business enterprises--Maryland--Maryville.; Cabinetwork.; Genealogy.; Medicine.; Real estate business--Maryland--Maryville.; Reunions--United States.; Surveying.; Teaching.; Veterans--United States.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1933.
Occupations
Businessmen.; Soldiers.
Provenance
The papers of Nathaniel Sisson, Union soldier and businessman, were given to the Library of Congress by Lauris M. Eek in 2006.
Transfers
A photograph and a hand-painted miniature have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Nathaniel Sisson Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Nathaniel Sisson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1845, May 25 Born, Meigs County, Ohio
1862 1865 Bugler, Company A, Second West Virginia Voluntary Cavalry
1866 Teacher, Maryville, Mo.
1871 Civil engineer, C. Baker & Co., St. Joseph, Mo.
1874 Married Mary S. Hughes (died 1909)
1875 1930 Businessman, real estate companies, Maryville, Mo.
1882 Congressional nominee, Greenback-Labor Party
1892 Congressional nominee, Republican Party
1909 Chairman, Maryville Public Utilities Commission, Maryville, Mo.
1932, Sept. 17 Died, Maryville, Mo.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Nathaniel Sisson (1845-1932) span the years 1838-1932, with the bulk of the material dating from 1862 to 1920. The collection includes correspondence, financial records, medals, printed matter, and writings and is arranged alphabetically by type of material or topic followed by miscellany and oversize.
The earliest correspondence, 1862-1865, contains letters between Sisson and his family describing his Civil War experiences and their domestic activities. The post-Civil War correspondence is composed chiefly of letters received by Sisson from his family in Ohio and Iowa. Subjects include the medical profession, teaching, and farming. Sisson’s business ventures and private life are occasionally mentioned.
After his war service, Sisson moved to Maryville, Missouri, where he experimented with several professions such as bridge building, cabinet making, surveying, and teaching before settling on the real estate business. A subject file contains primarily printed matter documenting Sisson’s involvement in these areas. The file also includes material relating to Sisson’s participation in genealogical research, military reunions, national politics, and the Freemasons.
A writings file contains Sisson’s reminiscences of his Civil War experiences. It also includes essays, poetry, and speeches by Sisson and others. A miscellany file comprises military and political badges, road and bridge surveys, and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1862-1869, (11 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1870-1897, (13 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1898-1927, (10 folders) (Box 3)
- Subject file (Box 4)
  - American Telegraphone Co., 1916-1926 See also Oversize, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Biographical and genealogical material, 1900-1932 (Box 4)
  - Bridges and roads, 1868-1876 See also Oversize (Box 4)
  - Businessmen and merchants, 1869-1896 (Box 4)
  - Education, 1838, 1857-1868, 1891-1905 (Box 4)
  - Masonic material, 1850, 1882, 1893-1897, 1920 (Box 4)
  - Military, 1862-1868, 1874-1924, (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - Politics and political issues (Box 6)
    - 1870-1884, (7 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1890-1918, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - World War I memorial, 1919 (Box 7)
- Writings file (Box 7)
  - Essays, 1866-1880 (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Letters to the editor, 1884, 1908-1911, 1924 (Box 7)
  - Miscellany, 1866-1884 (Box 7)
  - Plays, undated (Box 7)
  - Poetry, 1901-1917 (Box 8)
  - Speeches, 1906-1911, (3 folders) (Box 8)
- Miscellany (Box 8)
  - Account book, 1874 (Box 8)
  - Badges and ribbons (Box 8)
    - Military, 1895-1913, 1920-1924, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Miscellany, 1891-1904 (Box 9)
    - Political, 1884, 1906-1912, 1920 (Box 9)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 9)
  - Fraternal organizations, 1886-1889 (Box 9)
  - List of names, undated (Box 9)
  - Memorabilia, 1862, 1881 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1847, 1860-1869, 1879-1930 See also Oversize, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Printed matter, 1881, 1908, 1926-1932 (Box 10)
  - Public utilities commission, Maryville, Mo., 1908 (Box 10)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Subject file (Box OV 1)
    - American Telegraphone Co. (Box OV 1)
      - Printed matter, 1917-1924 (Box OV 1)
    - Bridges and roads (Box OV 2)
      - Bridge elevations, undated (Box OV 2)
  - Miscellany (Box OV 3)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box OV 3)
      - Set I, 1847-1869, 1883-1884 (Box OV 3)
      - Set II, 1905-1907, 1928 (Box OV 4)